<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - David L. Rappeport</title>
        <link>/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | David L. Rappeport</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>david.l.rappeport@gmail.com (David L Rappeport)</managingEditor>
            <webMaster>david.l.rappeport@gmail.com (David L Rappeport)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 18:28:25 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Diamonds Forever</title>
    <link>/diamonds-forever/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 18:28:25 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>/diamonds-forever/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Time for a brief personal note. On January 29th 2021, I took the big leap and proposed to my girlfriend, Emma, at L&rsquo;Auberge Resort in Sedona, Arizona. Thankfully, she said yes and we had an amazing weekend together. This photo below was taken by our photographer minutes after the proposal and captures a moment of pure bliss.
While I could definitely write more about the weekend we had, I am instead going to spend the rest of this post writing about something I wish I had found better information about online before I proposed, diamond engagement rings.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Hedonometer</title>
    <link>/hedonometer/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 14:10:46 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>/hedonometer/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Background About two months ago, I was introduced to a work of the University of Vermont Computational Story Lab called the Hedonometer. At its core, the Hedonometer is a large scale NLP application based on Twitter data and is used to measure &ldquo;happiness&rdquo; at scale. The creators do a great job summarizing this here:
 “What is being measured by the instrument?” hedonometer.org currently measures Twitter’s Decahose API feed (formerly Gardenhose).]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coming Soon</title>
    <link>/coming-soon/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 22:08:24 -0700</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>/coming-soon/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[This site is a work in progress. More content coming soon.]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
